{"tossups": [{"question": "As Acting Solicitor General, Neal Katyal released a 2011 statement accusing one of his predecessors, Charles Fahy, of covering up evidence relevant to this case. Justice Frank Murphy\u2019s dissent in this case, along with his concurrence in<em> Steele</em>, marked the first uses of the word \u201cracism\u201d in a Supreme Court opinion. The previous case of<em> Hirabayashi v. United States</em> was found to be controlling in Hugo Black\u2019s majority opinion in this case, which defended Executive Order 9066 as a legitimate use of executive discretion. For ten points, name this 1944 Supreme Court decision that upheld Japanese internment camps.", "answer": "<b> Korematsu</b> v. United States", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An axeman who legendarily killed 40 people at this battle was himself killed when a soldier underneath the bridge he stood on stabbed him through the planks. One attack during this battle was known as\u201cOrre\u2019s Storm.\u201d This battle, named for a location near the Derwent River, included the deaths of Tostig and the Norwegian king Harald Hardrada. For ten points, name this victory for the forces of Harold Godwinson which preceded the 1066 Battle of Hastings by five days.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Stamford Bridge</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A student at this school was expelled when he said a tutor named Whittlesey \u201chad no more grace than a chair.\u201d While under the leadership of Thomas Clapp, this university faced a conflict between the \u201cOld Lights\u201d and \u201cNew Lights.\u201d This university is named after a leader in the British East India Company, but it was known as the Collegiate School while it was located in Saybrook. The Skull and Bones secret society was formed at, for ten points, what Ivy League university that, in 1716, moved to New Haven, Connecticut?", "answer": "<b> Yale</b> University", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The publication of this work was preceded by a 9-page manuscript titled<em> De motu corporum in gyrum</em>, which was sent to Edmund Halley. The author of this work added a section containing the line \u201cI contrive no hypotheses\u201d to the end of this work\u2019s second edition, referred to as the General Scholium. This work contains a proof of Kepler\u2019s empirically derived laws of planetary motion. For ten points, name this book that introduced the three laws of motion and the law of universal gravitation, written by Sir Isaac Newton.", "answer": "(Philosophiae Naturalis)<b> Principia</b> Mathematica", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This man instructed his warriors to sing an enemy victory chant to lure out his opponent\u2019s defenses in the final defeat of his rival, Zwide [zwee-day]. This leader instructed his troops to envelop enemies while attacking in a \u201cbuffalo horns\u201d formation and introduced the tactic of offensive shield hooking while using a shorter, stabbing spear called the iklwa. Dingane [din-gah-nay] helped assassinate this chieftain in 1828. For ten points, name this early leader of the Zulu kingdom.", "answer": "<b> Shaka</b> Zulu (or<b> Shaka</b> kaSenzangakhona)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This body\u2019s legislation was stored in the treasury building, called the Aerarium. A common stalling tactic in this body was to continue speaking until nightfall. This body was forbidden from meeting more than a mile from the<em> pomerium</em>. The Catiline Conspiracy was exposed in a meeting of this body, whose actions could be vetoed by tribunes. Its members were appointed by the censors, often after holding offices like aedile and quaestor. For ten points, name this legislative body of Rome.", "answer": "<b> Roman Senate</b> (prompt on Senate alone until \u201cRome\u201d is said, then accept Senate)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "The location of this project was hotly contested by a board chaired for a time by Gouverneur Morris. A series of letters advocating this project were written under the pseudonym \u201cHercules\u201d by inmate Jesse Hawley. This project required the dangerous and costly draining of Montezuma Marsh. It was derisively nicknamed \u201cClinton\u2019s Ditch\u201d after then governor of New York DeWitt Clinton. For ten points, identify this waterway that, after 1821, connected Albany to a namesake great lake bordering Buffalo.", "answer": "<b> Erie Canal</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. A key piece of evidence in this lawsuit was the \u201cPorter Presentation,\u201d which supposedly made Pete Rozelle \u201cphysically ill.\u201d Though the plaintiff in this case was awarded victory, the jury only awarded damages of one dollar, which was tripled because the case involved antitrust law. In the aftermath of this case, Donald Trump\u2019s New Jersey Generals and other teams suspended operations. For ten points, name this lawsuit filed by the USFL against its primary competitor, which was found to have created an anti-competitive business environment.", "answer": "<b> NFL monopoly</b> case (accept<b> United States Football League v. National Football League</b>, or<b> USFL v. NFL</b>, or descriptions of \u201cthe USFL\u2019s lawsuit,\u201d before USFL is named; accept antitrust for monopoly before antitrust is mentioned; prompt on \u201cthe NFL\u2019s lawsuit\u201d and similar)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Senator from Maine named William Frye was one negotiator of this treaty, whose fifth article limited the commissions of both sides to five people. One year before this treaty was signed, one side had signed the Pact of Biak-no-Bato with a revolutionary group. The Platt Amendment concerned a territory ceded by this treaty, which gave Puerto Rico and Guam to the United States. One side relinquished Cuba in, for ten points, what 1898 treaty ending the Spanish-American War?", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Paris</b> of 1898", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician\u2019s brother, Erik Prince, founded the private military firm Academi, originally named Blackwater. In a Congressional hearing, this politician was mocked for praising guns for defense in case of bear attacks. Susan Collins and Lisa Murkowski crossed party lines to vote against this figure\u2019s confirmation, requiring the tie to be broken by Mike Pence. For ten points, name this proponent of charter schools and current US Secretary of Education.", "answer": "Betsy<b> DeVos</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "One holder of this position expanded his capital city to include Janiculum Hill, while another holder of this position created the Tribal Assembly for the lower classes. Holders of this position repeatedly fought against Veii [way-ee] and destroyed the city of Alba Longa. The last holder of this position was overthrown by Lucius Junius Brutus after the Rape of Lucretia. Julius Caesar was assassinated because the conspirators thought he wanted to revive, for ten points, what position held by the first seven rulers of Rome?", "answer": "<b> King of Rome</b> (accept<b> King</b> alone after \u201cRome\u201d is read at the end of the question; prompt on generic descriptions like ruler of Rome; do not accept emperor of Rome or other specific non-King titles)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "An event in this US state was the subject of Heather Ann Thompson\u2019s 2016 book<em> Blood in the Water</em> and was discussed by the mostly sealed Meyer Report. A 19th century facility in this state developed a system of solitary confinement and prison labor called the Auburn system. William Quinn was one of ten corrections officers killed in this state in a 1971 prison riot that ended with this state\u2019s police killing 33 prisoners. For ten points, name this state where Governor Nelson Rockefeller put down the Attica prison riot.", "answer": "<b> New York</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Although not the unconscious, Cote and Levine studied the \u201ccollective\u201d form of this concept. It was broken down into 8 separate challenges by a psychologist who wrote biographies of Mohandas Gandhi and Martin Luther focused on this concept. Stages of this psychological concept, which include autonomy vs. shame and industry vs. inferiority, were included in Erik Erikson\u2019s model of it. For ten points, name this psychological concept of one\u2019s self, which can experience a namesake \u201ccrisis.\u201d", "answer": "<b> identity</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler ordered the execution of Waldensians at the Massacre of M\u00b4erindol. After this ruler\u2019s victory at the Battle of Marignano, this leader signed the Perpetual Peace with Switzerland. This ruler\u2019s blockade of Nice was aided by an Ottoman fleet, to which he had leased the port of Toulon. This man reneged on the Treaty of Madrid, which had ceded Burgundy and Provence to his neighbor, as soon as he was released from captivity. For ten points, name this French king of the Valois dynasty who lost the Battle of Pavia to Charles V.", "answer": "<b> Francis I</b> (or<b> Fran\u00b8cois I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This island is home to a Methodist camp known for its gingerbread cottages, Wesleyan Grove. This island, which comprises the bulk of Dukes County, was home to a village sign</b> <b>language that died out in the 1950s. John F. Kennedy Jr. (+)</b> <b>died in a plane crash off</b> <b>this island\u2019s coast, and depending on tides, this island is sometimes connected to a smaller island where (*) </b> Mary Jo Kopechne died in the Chappaquiddick Incident. For ten points, name this resort island off the south coast of mainland Massachusetts and west of Nantucket.", "answer": "<b> Martha\u2019s Vineyard</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "13 of a work written in this language is interpreted as expressing either</b> <b>monotheism, atheism, or polytheism. Arthur Schopenhauer\u2019s translations of several works in this language led him to call them the \u201cproduction of the highest human wisdom.\u201d (+) Robert Oppenheimer supposedly learned this language just to read one of its most famous works, which he quoted after the Trinity nuclear test. The (*)</b><em> Upanishads</em>,<em> Bhagavad Gita</em>, and <em>Mahabharata</em> were all written in, for ten points, what ancient Indian language used in Hindu, Buddhist, and Jain traditions?", "answer": "<b> Sanskrit</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>One performer of this instrument wrote a song in protest of a segregationist Governor of Arkansas that was originally recorded as an instrumental, \u201cFables of Faubus.\u201d That performer of this instrument also wrote the prehistoric-themed jazz tone poem (+) </b><em><b>Pithecanthropus Erectus</b></em><b>. Charlie Haden played this instrument, as did the composer of</b><em><b> The </b><b>Black Saint and the Sinner Lady</b></em><b>, Charles (*)</b> Mingus. This instrument can play a \u201cwalking\u201d line and is often played with a \u201cslap\u201d pizzicato in jazz. For ten points, name this largest and lowest-pitched string instrument.", "answer": "double<b> bass</b> (or upright<b> bass</b> or acoustic<b> bass</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In an epic poem set in this country, a group of exiles send a message to an old leader by writing their names on a thousand pieces of wood and casting them into the sea. While sick, the body of an evil poetic character from this country is so feverish that it turns (+) water to fire. A poem from this country is about a hut that \u201cMay change with a new owner / Into a doll\u2019s house\u201d and opens the collection (*) </b> <em>Narrow Road to the Deep North</em>. The Taira and Minamoto clans clash in<em> The Tale of the Heike</em>, an epic poem from this country. For ten points, name this home country of Matsuo Basho, a poet who wrote many haiku.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "<b>On the way to this event, the victim was given a book of psalms by Henry Edgeworth. A publication called the</b><em><b> Daily Thermometer</b></em><b> claimed that the victim of this event exclaimed \u201cI am lost!\u201d Antoine-Joseph Santerre hastened this event by calling a (+) drumroll, drowning out its victim\u2019s speech. Charles-Henri Sanson carried out this event, one and a half years after its victim was recognized by Jean-Bapiste Drouet during the (*)</b> flight to Varennes and nine months before its victim\u2019s wife suffered the same fate. The guillotine was employed in, for ten points, what 1793 killing of a French monarch?", "answer": "<b> execution of Louis XVI</b> [16] (accept equivalents for execution, including<b> beheading</b>, <b>killing</b>, etc.; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}